Guide to the W.H. Cowley Papers SC0196
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Personal papers and writings, Series 1
  - Correspondence, writings and speeches, 1922-1978; Series 1B
    - Hamilton College Board of Trustees Report, 15 pages., 1943 Oct 9 (Box 14, Folder 43-4)
    - Description of WHC by Eve Dobson, WHC's secretary at Hamilton College, 10 pages., 1943 Jan (Box 14, Folder 43-5)
    - "The Liberal Arts College, WHC article," Dartmouth Alumni Magazine, pages 11-13., 1943 May (Box 14, Folder 43-6)
    - "Some are Leaders, Some are Headmen," WHC article, New York Times Magazine, 2 pages., 1943 Oct 17 (Box 14, Folder 43-7)
    - Correspondence about 43-7., 1943 Oct-1944 Jan (Box 14, Folder 43-7A)
    - "Report of the American Association of Colleges Commission on Liberal Education," written by Baxter, James P., Bulletin of Association of American Colleges, pages 269-299., 1943 May (Box 14, Folder 43-8)
    - Letter to Osborn, Alex F. about student opinion of WHC, Hamilton., 1943 Sep-1943 Dec (Box 14, Folder 43-9)
    - Papers about the Couper Board-Faculty Conference, Hamilton College, 42 pages. See also 43-17. (Box 14, Folder 43-10)
    - "Responsible Cooperation," WHC charge to the Hamilton class of 1943, Hamilton Alumni Review, page 251 and School and Society, pages 113-114. (Box 14, Folder 43-11)
    - WHC study of Hamilton College Faculty compensation and related correspondence, 100 pages., 1943 (Box 14, Folder 43-12)
    - WHC letter to The Presbyterian Tribune, page 3, in response to an editorial of May entitled "Blackout of Culture.", 1943 Jun (Box 14, Folder 43-13)
    - WHC notes for unwritten memo to the Hamilton Board of Trustees, 30 pages., undated (Box 14, Folder 43-14)
    - Correspondence with Adams, Samuel Hopkins., 1943 Oct-1945 Nov (Box 14, Folder 43-15)
    - "What is This Thing Called Love?" Outline for WHC sermon at Peddie School. Also given on Pearl Harbor Day, at Middlebury College., 1941, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 43-16)
    - WHC letters to Daniel Burke and Edgar W. Couper, plus related papers, about Hamilton situation., 1943 (Box 14, Folder 43-17)
    - WHC memorandum about Campbell Dickson's drinking problem., 1943 (Box 14, Folder 43-18)
    - Newspaper report of grant from Carnegie Corporation for WHC to write a book on liberal education., 1943 Apr 18 (Box 14, Folder 43-19)
    - Papers related to Hamilton's wartime programs., 1943 May-Jun (Box 14, Folder 43-20)
    - Honarary degree awarded to WHC by St. Lawrence University, news report., 1943 Oct 22 (Box 14, Folder 43-21)
    - Hamilton College Board of Trustees Report., 1943 Jan 30 (Box 14, Folder 43-22)
    - Hamilton College Board of Trustees Report., 1943 Apr 17 (Box 14, Folder 43-23)
    - WHC message to Hamilton graduating seniors. Hamilton Alumni Review, pages 128-130. Citation only. WHC did not keep a copy., 1943 (Box 14, Folder 43-24)
    - Honorary degree citation for Saunders, A.P., Hamilton Alumni Review, page 252. Citation only. WHC did not keep a copy., 1943 Jul (Box 14, Folder 43-25)
    - "Freedom and Discipline," The Educational Record, pages 5-22.See also 44-8., 1944 Jan (Box 14, Folder 44-1)
    - Comments and correspondence on 44-1., 1944 (Box 14, Folder 44-1A)
    - "The Power Revolution," chapter 1 of WHC's unpublished manuscript written with Carnegie Foundation support., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-2)
    - "Physical Changes," chapter 2 of WHC unpublished manuscript written with Carnegie Foundation support., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-3)
    - "Social Change," chapter 3 of unpublished manuscript, Carnegie Corporation., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-4)
    - "The Have-Nots Struggle for Power," chapter 4 of unpublished Carnegie supported manuscript., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-5)
    - "The Soul of America," WHC address before the New York Chapter of Life Insurance Underwriters, Think., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-6)
    - Correspondence about 44-6., 1944 Jan-1945 Apr (Box 15, Folder 44-6A)
    - Papers regarding Hamilton College faculty salaries including the report of the Nesbitt Committee, and WHC's analysis of the report, 25 pages., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-7)
    - Correspondence with Sproul, Robert G.. See also 44-1., 1944 Mar-Apr (Box 15, Folder 44-8)
    - Papers regarding WHC's resignation from Hamilton College: (Box 15, Folder 44-9)
    - Correspondence with Raitt, R.G.., 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-9A)
    - Correspondence with Hamilton faculty and staff., 1944 Aug-Nov (Box 15, Folder 44-9B)
    - Correspondence with Hamilton Board of Trustees., 1944 Aug-Nov (Box 15, Folder 44-9C)
    - Correspondence with Hamilton alumni., 1941-1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-9D)
    - Correspondence with friends and colleagues., 1944 Aug-Dec (Box 15, Folder 44-9E)
    - WHC diary entries., 1944 Sep-Nov (Box 15, Folder 44-9F)
    - Report of the Rockefellor consultant on some problems of Hamilton College, 3 pages. Includes correspondence., 1942, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-9G)
    - Correspondence and notes about the Couper Committee, Hamilton., 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-10)
    - Correspondence about the Hamilton College presidency. MISSING, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 44-11)
    - Correspondence about WHC's appointment to the Stanford University Faculty., 1944-1945 (Box 15, Folder 44-12)
    - Salary records from Stanford University., 1946-1967 (Box 16, Folder 44-12A)
    - WHC's secretary's manual, Dobson, Evelyn., 1944 (Box 16, Folder 44-13)
    - WHC letter to Smith, T.V. on morality., 1944 (Box 16, Folder 44-14)
    - Correspondence with Conant, James Bryant about possibility of WHC sojourn in Cambridge, Massachusetts., 1944 Apr-Oct (Box 16, Folder 44-15)
    - Hamilton College Alumni Fund letter., 1944 Feb 10 (Box 16, Folder 44-16)
    - Text of President Roosevelt message approving a plan for the use of the colleges by the Armed Forces., 1944 Mar 3-4 (Box 16, Folder 44-17)
    - Papers about two job offers in the U.S. Office of War Information and the U.S. Office of strategic Services., 1944 (Box 16, Folder 44-18)
    - Correspondence with Morrill, J.L. and the presidency of the University of Minnesota., 1944 May-Nov (Box 16, Folder 44-19)
    - Report to the Hamilton College Trustees., 1944 Jan 29 (Box 16, Folder 44-20)
    - Report to the Hamilton College Trustees., 1944 Apr 15 (Box 16, Folder 44-21)
    - "The Significance of the Harvard Report for Secondary Schools," text of Western College Association Address, 5 pages. Also related correspondence., 1945-1946 (Box 16, Folder 45-1)
    - Terminal report to the Board of Trustees of Hamilton College. Written by WHC in Columbus Ohio, 340 pages., 1945 Spring (Box 16, Folder 45-2)
    - "The Old Scorns the New," chapter 2 of Carnegie supported book on liberal education, first draft, 21 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-3)
    - "The Old American College: Purposes," chapter 2 of liberal education manuscript, second draft, 21 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-3A)
    - "The Power Revolution," chapter 3 of liberal education manuscript, 29 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-4)
    - "Five Great Pressures," chapter 4 of unfinished liberal education manuscript, 37 pages. Note: THIS FOLDER MISSING, 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-5)
    - "The German Infiltration," chapter 5 of unfinished liberal education manuscript, 32 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-6)
    - "The German Infiltration," chapter 5 of liberal education manuscript, 32 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-7)
    - "The Seven Liberal Arts Hoax," magazine article offered for publication to the American Mercury, 9 pages. See also 45-19 and 45-37., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-8)
    - Correspondence with President Conant, James Bryant of Harvard about "General Education in a Free Society." Also includes correspondence with Hollinshead, Byron., 1945 Jul-Nov (Box 16, Folder 45-9)
    - Correspondence with Buck, Paul H. Chairman of the Harvard Committee on the Objectives of General Education in a Free Society., 1943 Jun-1946 May (Box 16, Folder 45-10)
    - Miscellaneous papers on the importance of history and a proposal to the American Council on Education., 1943, 1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 45-11)
    - "The Harvard Report on General Education," WHC article published in the Stanford University School of Education Alumni Newsletter, pages 7-8., 1945 Nov (Box 16, Folder 45-12)
    - "The Report in Perspective," WHC article published in the Harvard Alumni Bulletin, pages 27-28., 1945 Sep 22 (Box 16, Folder 45-13)
    - "Challenge to Physical Education," WHC article, Journal of Higher Education, pages175-177., 1945 Apr (Box 16, Folder 45-14A)
    - "The Broad Educational Problems of Physical Educators," WHC article, Health and Physical Education, pages 325-350., 1945 Jun (Box 16, Folder 45-14B)
    - "The Broad Educational Problems of Physical Educators," WHC address published in the 48th Annual Proceedings of College Physical Educational Association, pages 19-21., 1944-1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-14C)
    - Student comments on WHC's student personnel course, Education 327., 1945 Fall (Box 16, Folder 45-15)
    - Student comments on WHC course, Education 222., 1945 Fall (Box 16, Folder 45-15A)
    - Correspondence with Corbett, R. H. about his criticism of WHC's article on the Harvard Report., 1945 Nov (Box 16, Folder 45-16)
    - "The College Under Fire," chapter 1 version of WHC's Carnegie Corporation supported book on liberal education, first draft, 22 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-17)
    - WHC book review of Frontier Thinking in Guidance, edited by Yale, John R., Registar's Journal., 1945 Oct (Box 16, Folder 45-18)
    - "Verbalisms from the Past," chapter 3 of liberal education book, 37 pages plus "Aristoleian Science: Another Version or Supplement of Present Text Herein," 10 pages. See also 45-8 and 45-37., 1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 45-19)
    - "Random Thoughts After Reading Niebuhr's Moral Man and Immoral Society," 5 pages., 1945 Jan (Box 16, Folder 45-20)
    - "Personnel Work in Education: Perspective and Prophecy," abstract of WHC talk at the Western Personnel Service Conference, 1 page., 1945 Nov 2 (Box 16, Folder 45-21)
    - Miscellaneous writing about intellectual power, 16 pages., 1945 (Box 16, Folder 45-22)
    - "Moral Responsibility," WHC article, Columbus Ohio, 1945, 8 pages. Also includes handwritten draft. (Box 16, Folder 45-23)
    - Correspondence with Boodin, John Elof about his article, "Nature and Reason," in Contemporary American Philosophy., 1945 Jan 23 (Box 16, Folder 45-24)
    - "The Re-education of Germany," transcript of WHC address, Tuesday Evening lecture Series, Stanford University, 32 pages. Also includes correspondence and newsclippings about talk., 1945 May-Jul (Box 16, Folder 45-25)
    - WHC book review for the Journal of Higher Education, of Jacques Barzun's Teacher in America., 1945 Jun (Box 16, Folder 45-26)
    - Adams, Samuel Hopkins correspondence about WHC's liberal education manuscript., 1945 Mar-1952 Mar (Box 17, Folder 45-27)
    - Correspondence with Graves, Edgar B.. See also 39-7, 39-13, 42-19., 1944-1946 (Box 17, Folder 45-28)
    - Correspondence with Morrill, J.L. about his election as President of the University of Minnesota, See also, 44-19 and 46-14., 1945 (Box 17, Folder 45-29)
    - Correspondence with Williamson, E. G. concerning possibility of Williamson joining the faculty of Stanford University., 1945-1946 (Box 17, Folder 45-30)
    - Pre-publication book review done by WHC for Ginn & Co. Author of manuscript not recorded., 1945 (Box 17, Folder 45-31)
    - Correspondence with Janeway, Eliot about education., 1945 Mar-Dec (Box 17, Folder 45-32)
    - Correspondence with President Day, E. E. of Cornell. See also 45-29., 1944 Apr-1950 Feb (Box 17, Folder 45-33)
    - Correspondence with Hamilton alumnus, Taylor, Frank of Reynall and Hitchcock publishing., 1944 Aug-1945 Jul (Box 17, Folder 45-34)
    - Outgoing correspondence with J.B. Conant and Paul Buck about the Harvard Report on general education and possibility of their coming to speak at Stanford. Also includes initial correspondence about Conant's Sachs lectures., 1945-1946 Jul (Box 17, Folder 45-35)
    - "An Approach to the College Problem," chapter 2 version of liberal education manuscript, 14 pages., 1945 (Box 17, Folder 45-36)
    - "Verbalisms from the Past," chapter 3 version of liberal education manuscript. See also 45-8 and 45-19. MISSING, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 45-37)
    - "The Harvard Report: A Review," WHC article, Harvard Educational Review, pages 56-71., 1946 Jan (Box 17, Folder 46-1)
    - Correspondence about publication of 46-1., 1945 Aug-1946 Oct (Box 17, Folder 46-1A)
    - "Education for the Great Community," WHC article, Journal of General Education, pages 22-33. Also includes related correspondence., 1946, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 46-2)
    - "Education for the Great Community," text of WHC address at the Utah Higher Education, 14 pages., 1946 Sep (Box 17, Folder 46-2A)
    - "Brothers Under the Sheepskin", text of WHC address at the Stanford University Educational Conference, 21 pages. (Same as 46-2 except for title)., 1946 Jul (Box 17, Folder 46-3)
    - "Conflicts in College and University General Education," text of WHC address at Stanford Humanities Symposium, 29 pages. Also includes correspondence about the talk., 1946 May-Jun (Box 17, Folder 46-4)
    - "The Junior College Confusion," WHC address at the Utah Higher Education Conference. See also 46-2 and 46-16., 1946 Sep 13 (Box 17, Folder 46-5)
    - "What is a College Subject in Education and Psychology?" text of WHC address at the Fall meeting of the Western College Association, 18 pages. See also 47-2., 1946 Nov 16 (Box 17, Folder 46-6)
    - WHC analysis of Seligman, E.R.A. and the great man theory of history, Stanford, 13 pages. See also 46-22., 1946 Oct (Box 17, Folder 46-7)
    - Correspondence with Schlamm, William S. about WHC's projected new magazine for Time Inc.., 1945 Jul-1948 Feb (Box 17, Folder 46-8)
    - "The Education of the Larger Self," text of WHC Speech at the Northwest Conference on Higher Education, Oregon state. Includes closing discussion and summary of the conference and an evaluation by the participants, 16 pages., 1946 Jul 12-13 (Box 17, Folder 46-9)
    - "Political Power," chapter 7 version of 1945 of liberal education manuscript, 15 pages., 1946 (Box 17, Folder 46-10)
    - "Economic Power," chapter 7 of 1945 version of liberal education manuscript, 15 pages., 1946 (Box 17, Folder 46-11)
    - "New Era in Education," speech written by WHC for Kratt, William E., 18 pages., 1946 (Box 17, Folder 46-12)
    - Correspondence with Conant, J.B. about WHC's analysis of his Sachs lectures., 1945 Aug-1946 Dec (Box 17, Folder 46-13)
    - Copy of Conant's Sachs lectures, Teachers College Record., 1945 Dec (Box 17, Folder 46-13A)
    - "Analysis of the Sachs Lecures of J.B. Conant," 96 pages. Also correspondence related to this work., 1946 Summer (Box 18, Folder 46-13B)
    - Worksheets analyzing General Education in a Free Society. See also 46-2 and 46-16. Oversize, filed at end of Series I-B. (Box 18, Folder 46-13C)
    - Correspondence with Morrill, J. L. including WHC proposed inaugural address outline at request., 1946 Jan-1947 Apr (Box 18, Folder 46-14)
    - "The College Under Fire," chapter 1 of Carnegie version of liberal arts manuscript, 1946, 22 pages. (Box 18, Folder 46-15)
    - WHC worksheets analyzing "Education for All American Youth.", 1946 (Box 18, Folder 46-16)
    - "Six Plans for General Education," text of WHC address at the Utah Higher Education Conference, University of Utah, 35 pages. Also includes newsclipppings about the conference., 1946 (Box 18, Folder 46-16A)
    - Minutes of WHC higher education seminar, Stanford., 1946 Spring (Box 18, Folder 46-17)
    - Projected article on Cole, C.W. later president of Amherst, notes and correspondence., 1946 Feb-1947 Mar (Box 18, Folder 46-18)
    - "Technological Power," chapter 5 of Stanford version of liberal arts manuscript, 23 pages. (Box 18, Folder 46-19)
    - Correspondence with Hutchinson, Paul editor of The Christian Century, concerning Monsignor Sheen., 1946 Feb-Mar (Box 18, Folder 46-20)
    - "Counseling and Social Claustration," correspondence regarding WHC talk at UCLA. Does not contain text of speech., 1946 Apr 6 (Box 18, Folder 46-21)
    - "Analysis of E.R.A. Seligman's Treatment of Marxism," in the Economic Interpretation of History, unpublished manuscript, 5 typed pages. See also 46-7. (Box 18, Folder 46-22)
    - WHC discussions of equality, four unpublished drafts., 1946 Nov-Dec (Box 18, Folder 46-23)
    - "A Plan of Attack," chapter 3, first version of Carnegie manuscript, 9 pages., 1946 (Box 18, Folder 46-24)
    - "The Essential Fact," chapter 4 of first version of Carnegie manuscript, 11 pages., 1946 (Box 18, Folder 46-25)
    - Correspondence with Wallace, Dewitt of Readers Digest about WHC's ideas for articles., 1946 Apr-Nov (Box 18, Folder 46-26)
    - Student ratings of WHC's teaching., 1946 Summer (Box 18, Folder 46-27)
    - Correspondence with Hullfish, H. Gordon about WHC article on the Harvard Report, and about WHC speech, "What is a College Subject in Education and Psychology." See also 46-6., 1946 Aug-1947 Apr (Box 18, Folder 47-1)
    - Correspondence with Charters, W. W. including a discussion of WHC's "What is a College Subject in Education and Psychology." See also 46-6 and 47-1., 1944 Dec-1948 Dec (Box 18, Folder 47-2)
    - "Plan of the Book," chapter 3 of 1946 Carnegie manuscript, 28 pages. (Box 18, Folder 47-3)
    - "The Old American College," chapter 4 of 1946 version of WHC's Carnegie manuscript, 47 pages., 1947 (Box 18, Folder 47-4)
    - "A New Age Begins," chapter 5 of 6th version of Carnegie manuscript, 53 pages., 1947 (Box 18, Folder 47-5)
    - "The Government and Administration of Higher Education Whence and Whither?" WHC article, Journal of American Assoication of Collegiate Registrars, pages 277-291. Includes related correspondence., 1947 (Box 18, Folder 47-6)
    - "San Diego's Next Fifty Years," transcript of WHC address delivered at San Diego State University, 24 pages., 1947 May 11 (Box 18, Folder 47-7)
    - "Report of W.H. Cowley to the University of the Redlands," personnel survey conducted by WHC for the University of Redlands, 8 pages., 1947 Apr (Box 18, Folder 47-8)
    - "All God's Chillun Wings," WHC article, School and Society, pages 145-150. Also contains related correspondence., 1947 (Box 18, Folder 47-9)
    - "Curriculum of Higher Education," outlines of three lectures in the Hanna-Bartky Course, Education 140, 14 pages., 1947 Aug (Box 18, Folder 47-10)
    - "Who is to Blame?" chapter 2 of 5th, 6th and 7th versions of Carnegie funded manuscript, 15 pages., 1947 (Box 18, Folder 47-11)
    - Correspondence with Sargent, Porter about possiblity of WHC taking over the publication of Sargent's "Handbook to Private Schools" series., 1947-1951 (Box 19, Folder 47-12)
    - "Some History and Venture in Prophecy," WHC article Trends in Student Personnel Work, edited by Williamson, E.G., pages 12-27. Also contains related correspondence., 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 47-13)
    - "Jabberwocky versus Maturity," WHC article, Trends in Student Personnel Work, edited by Williamson ,E.G., pages 342-350., 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-14)
    - "The Structure of the Academic System," chapter 10, 7th and 9th version of Carnegie funded manuscript, 28 pages. See also 47-32., 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-15)
    - Personnel survey of Lewis and Clark College, 13 pages. Contains letter from WHC to President Odell, Morgan S. giving WHC's observations of the college and a report written by Professor Gilchrist, F.G. about counseling at the college., 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-16)
    - "Maintaining Quality in the Face of Increasing Numbers," text of WHC address, Western College Association Addresses, pages 901-919. Also reproduced in a book by Valentine, F. P. See also 49-11., 1947 Nov 15 (Box 19, Folder 47-17)
    - Correspondence with Conant, J.B., 1947 Jan-Apr (Box 19, Folder 47-18)
    - "Point of View and Terminology," chapter 3, 6th version of Carnegie funded manuscript, 27 pages. See also 47-3., 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 47-19)
    - Little, Arlene worksheets. MISSING, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-20)
    - A model summary of an article written by WHC for his students, 5 pages., 1947 Jun (Box 19, Folder 47-21)
    - Correspondece with and about Karl With's efforts to find a position away from Hamilton College., 1945-1948 (Box 19, Folder 47-22)
    - Papers relating to a dozen or so speeches for which WHC kept no outlines., 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-23)
    - Correspondence with Elliott, R. M. about 1941 invitation from the University of Minnesota for WHC to be president. Includes important discussion Minnesota's Board of Trustees Chairman, Snyder., 1947 Nov-1948 Feb (Box 19, Folder 47-24)
    - Correspondence with Kandel, I.l about WHC article, "The Re-Education of Germany." Copy of article also included., 1947 Jan-Feb (Box 19, Folder 47-25)
    - Correspondence with Chapin, F. Stuart, Minnesota sociologist about student mores., 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 47-26)
    - Correspondence with Smith, T.V. about his School and Society article on Catholicism in Italy., 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-27)
    - WHC analysis of John Henry Newman's 6th discourse, "The Idea of a University.", 1945, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 47-28)
    - Correspondence with Jones, Richard Lloyd during the 1940's about wartime programs at small college, WHC's problems at Hamilton College, and R. l. Jones' childhood. (Box 19, Folder 47-29)
    - Correspondence with Conant, J.B. about educational structuring., 1947 Jul-1948 Apr (Box 19, Folder 47-30)
    - "The Old College Overwhelmed," chapter 6, 2nd version of Carnegie funded manuscript., 1946 (Box 19, Folder 47-31)
    - "Other Systems of Higher Education," outline for possible inclusion in Carnegie manuscript and related correspondence. See also 47-15., 1947 Oct-Dec (Box 19, Folder 47-32)
    - Miscellaneous material for Carnegie manuscript, 96 pages., 1947 Sep-Oct (Box 19, Folder 47-33)
    - Correspondence with Maclean, Max., 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 48-1)
    - "The Curriculum of Higher Education," summaries of four lectures by WHC for Paul Hanna's course, 32 pages., 1948 Feb (Box 19, Folder 48-2)
    - "Preparation and Professional Growth of College Teachers," text of WHC address to the National Education Association's Conference on Higher Education., 1948 Mar 22 (Box 19, Folder 48-3)
    - Correspondence with Buck-Jacoby Committee, appointed by the Rockefellor Foundation to examine the possibilities, the desirability, and the possible scope of a study of the problems involved in the finanancing of higher education and research in the United States., 1948, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 48-4)
    - "Tentative Thoughts on the Truman Committee Report," text of WHC speech to the National Association of State Universities, Chicago, pages 77- 78., 1948 May 6 (Box 19, Folder 48-5)
    - "Thoughts on the Truman Report," WHC article, Journal of Higher Education, pages 275-283., 1948 Jun (Box 19, Folder 48-6)
    - "The Curriculum of Higher Education," four lecture outlines prepared by WHC for Paul Hanna's course, 32 pages. See also 48-2., 1948 Summer (Box 19, Folder 48-7)
    - "The Past and Future of Student Personnel Work," text of WHC address to the Northwest College Personnel Association Convention, 19 pages., 1948 Mar (Box 19, Folder 48-8)
    - "Report on the Committee on Finance and Organization in the Pacific Coast States," from a conference on higher education sponsored by the Pacific Coast Committee of the American Council on Education, Berkeley., 1948 Jul (Box 20, Folder 48-9)
    - Notes on research versus teaching, begun. MISSING, 1948 Jul (Box 20, Folder 48-10)